<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><pubdate>20220930</pubdate><title>File Name</title><geoform>raster digital data</geoform></citeinfo></citation><descript><purpose>This geospatial dataset, the Regional Resource Kit, was created for the California Wildfire and Forest Resilience Task Force and for use by the many federal, state, and local efforts to restore resiliency to forests in California. It was assembled by a federal-state-university consortium that includes the Climate and Wildfire Institute (CWI),  USDA Forest Service Pacific Southwest Research Station(PSW). the Center for Ecosystem Climate Solutions (CECS) - UC Irvine, California Department of Forestry and Fire Protection (CAL FIRE) and partners at UC Berkeley. 

</purpose><supplinf>ACCEL project:
The USDA Forest Service, in collaboration with the California Natural Resources Agency and other partners, is committed to increasing the “pace and scale” of forest treatments in California. Multiple federal and state initiatives in the last few years detail this commitment. Land managers need support to plan and implement treatments that will address restoration at a landscape scale.  
An essential component of these initiatives is the spatial data representing landscape conditions and new analytical tools for planning management investments. The Pacific Southwest Research Station (PSW) scientists and staff from Region 5 Information Management, Mapping and Remote Sensing (MARS) Team, joined forces to develop and/or collect and assemble existing sources of spatial data. This project, referred to as the ACCEL project (for accelerating pace and scale of treatments), combines the expertise and experience of research and management to build this library of data on landscape conditions. 
These data reflect landscape conditions across ten “Pillars of Resilience” which address the full array of landscape management objectives. 

• Pillars are the desired long-term, landscape-scale outcomes of restoring resilience. They include ecological values, such as biodiversity, as well as societal benefits to communities, such as water security. 

• Elements represent the primary processes and functions that altogether make up a pillar, such as focal species, water quality, or economic health. 

• Metrics describe the characteristics of elements in quantitative or qualitative terms. Users can use metrics to assess, plan for, measure, and monitor progress towards desired outcomes and greater resilience. While pillars and elements are consistent across the Sierra Nevada, the metrics that a group uses may vary from region to region based on ecological and social differences (for example forest types, economy), available data, and user preferences.

The ten pillars are Forest Resilience, Water Security, Carbon Sequestration, Air Quality, Fire Dynamics, Fire Adapted Communities, Economic Diversity, Social &amp; Cultural Well-Being, Wetland Integrity, Biodiversity Conservation.

The individual “Metrics”  are used to assess, plan for, measure, and monitor progress toward desired outcomes and greater resilience. Metrics are selected to be informative, meaningful, and actionable to meet the needs of management.
Landscape level assessment using these high-quality data, combined with decision support tools that can help evaluate alternative treatment strategies, are fundamental to inform and support large landscape restoration planning. These data are assembled in one place to provide comprehensive access for land managers. They represent conditions as of 2022 and intentions are to refresh these data on an annual basis. 
Each metric is defined to help the end-users of the data (and for use with any decision support tools) to understand:
• The definition meant by a given metric
• The expected use(s) of the metric 
• The resolution of the developed data
• The data sources used to derive the metric
• The intended method of metric derivation
• Where reasonable, a desired management target

References have been included to help the reader understand methods used for deriving metrics. This information will help people make better use of all the assembled information and how it can best be used with various decision support tools. The metric dictionary that accompanies this set of data will be updated periodically, as necessary.

</supplinf></descript><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Unknown</update></status><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt><themekey>environment</themekey><themekey>geoscientificInformation</themekey><themekey>planningCadastre</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Appropriate use includes regional to assessments of vegetation cover, land cover, or land use change trends, total extent of vegetation cover, land cover, or land use change, and aggregated summaries of vegetation cover, land cover, or land use change. Further use includes applying these data to assess management opportunities for treatments to restore landscape resiliency.The USDA Forest Service makes no warranty, expressed or implied, including the warranties of merchantability and fitness for a particular purpose, nor assumes any legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, reliability, completeness, or utility of these geospatial data, or for the improper or incorrect use of these geospatial data. These geospatial data and related maps or graphics are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such. The data and maps may not be used to determine title, ownership, legal descriptions or boundaries, legal jurisdiction, or restrictions that may be in place on either public or private land. Natural hazards may or may not be depicted on the data and maps, and land users should exercise due caution. The data are dynamic and may change over time. The user is responsible to verify the limitations of the geospatial data and to use the data accordingly.For all data layers you are free to share, copy, and redistribute the material in any medium or format AND adapt, remix, transform, and build upon the material for any purpose, even commercially under the following terms:Attribution — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use.ShareAlike — If you remix, transform, or build upon the material, you must distribute your contributions under the same license as the original.No additional restrictions — You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything this license permits.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>USDA Forest Service, Pacific Southwest Research Station</cntorg><cntper>Patricia Manley</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Research Program Manager</cntpos><cntemail>patricia.manley@usda.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><native>Esri ArcGIS 12.9.2.32739</native></idinfo><spdoinfo><direct>Raster</direct><rastinfo><rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype><rowcount>3300</rowcount><colcount>2550</colcount></rastinfo></spdoinfo><metainfo><metd>20221221</metd><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><mettc>local time</mettc></metainfo><mdChar><CharSetCd value="004" /></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd value="005" /></mdHrLv><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20240723</mdDateSt><mdStanName>ArcGIS Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer>1.0</mdStanVer><dataIdInfo><resConst><Consts><useLimit>&lt;DIV STYLE="text-align:Left;"&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;DIV&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 6 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;The user is responsible to verify the limitations of the geospatial data and to use the data accordingly. For all data layers, please check each data source and adhere to any limitations established by the data creator. In general, adhere to the terms for use listed at the bottom of this paragraph. The authors make no warranty, expressed or implied, including the warranties of merchantability and fitness for a particular purpose, nor assumes any legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, reliability, completeness, or utility of these geospatial data, or for the improper or incorrect use of these geospatial data. These geospatial data and related maps or graphics are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such. The data and maps may not be used to determine title, ownership, legal descriptions or boundaries, legal jurisdiction, or restrictions that may be in place on either public or private land. Natural hazards may or may not be depicted on the data and maps, and land users should exercise due caution. The data are dynamic and may change over time.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 6 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 6 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-weight:bold;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;Attribution&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt; — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 6 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 6 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-weight:bold;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;ShareAlike &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;— If you remix, transform, or build upon the material, you must distribute your contributions under the same license as the original. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 6 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 6 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-weight:bold;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;No commercial use&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt; – the user is responsible for acknowledging those data layers within this RRK (as determined by the source of the data) that are not permitted for commercial use. &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 6 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN /&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;P STYLE="margin:0 0 6 0;"&gt;&lt;SPAN STYLE="font-weight:bold;"&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;No additional restrictions&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt;&lt;SPAN&gt; — You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything this license permits.&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;&lt;/DIV&gt;</useLimit></Consts></resConst><envirDesc>Esri ArcGIS 12.9.2.32739</envirDesc><idPoC><rpPosName>Project Policy Analyst 5</rpPosName><rpOrgName>USDA California Climate Hub</rpOrgName><rpIndName>Peter A. Stine</rpIndName></idPoC><idPoC><rpPosName>Project Policy Analyst 4</rpPosName><rpOrgName>USDA California Climate Hub</rpOrgName><rpIndName>Carol Clark</rpIndName></idPoC><idCredit>Rocky Mountain Research Station, U.S. Forest Service
--Rocky Mountain Research Station, USDA Forest Service

</idCredit><idPurp>Landscape level assessments, using high-quality data combined with decision support tools to help evaluate alternative treatment strategies, are fundamental to inform and support large landscape restoration planning. This data layer, as part of the California Landscape Planning Metrics (CLPM) compilation, was created to provide comprehensive access for land managers. 

This layer was assembled/developed by a partnership that includes the USDA Forest Service Pacific Southwest Research Station (PSW), USDA Forest Service Region 5, the California Department of Forestry and Fire Protection (CAL FIRE) Fire and Resource Assessment Program (FRAP), the Climate and Wildfire Institute (CWI), and faculty from the University of California Berkeley and University of California Irvine. Subsequent efforts and activities will now also include the USDA California Climate Hub.  This science team worked together to build this library of geospatial data, originally called a Regional Resource Kit (RRK), at the behest of the California Wildfire and Forest Resilience Task Force. 

This metric is labeled as one of three "tiers." 

-Tier 1 - metrics that are a single, consistent data layer, developed statewide. Example:  Annual Burn Probability.
-Tier 2 - metrics relevant to and available for a single Region or relevant to multiple Regions but data layers differ among the Regions because of varied data availability (sources) across Regions. Example: California gnatcatcher habitat suitability.
-Tier 3 - metrics are those that would be of interest to some land managers for specific applications but not included in the as a core metric in the kit. Example: Distribution of the Quino checkerspot butterfly.

Some data layers within the CLPM contain null values. We point this out here so users of the data will be aware and take whatever measures appropriate as they use and analyze the data. For some raster datasets, areas have been masked (blanked) out and have a cell value of NoData (also referred to as null, NaN or missing). We, as producers and users of the data, cannot ignore NoData or fill them with zeros, since zero is often a valid value for some datasets. Removing NoData cells is not an option, a raster is a continuous grid. For users of the data performing further analyses and combining or "stacking" rasters, these NoData cells will mask out all values in that location in the output. To avoid this issue, the user must create values for the cells before combining them (i.e. 999 or any numeric value that is not real and clearly out of the range of the other values). Reasons for masking (blanking) out cells include:

-Cells are located in water bodies (e.g., lakes, reservoirs, or large rivers)
-Cells are located in urban areas
-Cells are located in areas used for irrigated agriculture
-Cells contain no information relevant to the dataset (e.g. for a streams data layer, areas outside of streams have NoData)
-Area (cells) subject to fire or other disturbance but the post disturbance condition or value is unknown.

Note that this data layer may have been masked (i.e. blocked out) for open water (lakes, reservoirs) and/or for the urban and agricultural landscape. This is done to avoid confusion with vegetation values coming from urban areas (e.g. city parks) or agricultural areas (e.g. irrigated farm land).

A file naming convention has been developed for the CLPM to help organize it and make a file easily identifiable. File naming definition:
&lt;regional prefix is included if applicable, none if statewide&gt;_&lt;description&gt;_&lt;vintage of source data, some may be a range of years&gt;_&lt;latest publish date&gt;_&lt;tier #&gt;_&lt;kit version #&gt;.&lt;file format&gt; 

Examples:
PotentialTotalSmoke_202209_202312_T1_v5.tif
NorCal_BiomassTrmntCostHigh_202309_202401_T2_v5.tif 
CumulTreeCoverLoss_19912020_202312_T1_v5.tif (this vintage represents a range from 1991 - 2020)

Use of prefixes
The following are the definitions for the four regional prefixes used in file naming. 
SNV = Sierra Nevada
SoCal = Southern California
CenCal = Central California
NorCal = Northern California

If a layer exists in every one of the four Task Force regions, it is Tier 1 and does not get a regional prefix. If a layer does not exist in every region but could if statewide coverage was available, it is Tier 2 and gets a regional prefix. If a layer does not exist in every region and it never could, it is Tier 2 and gets no prefix.</idPurp><idAbs>

- Metric Name:  Ignition Cause

- Tier:  1

- Data Vintage:  1992 - 2020

- Unit Of Measure: Categorical

- Metric Definition and Relevance:  The original point layer (WildfireOccurrence_CA_1992_2020.shp ) contains a spatial database of wildfires that occurred in the United States from 1992 to 2020. It is the fifth update of a publication originally generated to support the national Fire Program Analysis (FPA) system. The wildfire records were acquired from the reporting systems of federal, state, and local fire organizations. The following core data elements were required for records to be included in this data publication: discovery date, final fire size, and a point location at least as precise as a Public Land Survey System (PLSS) section (1-square mile grid). The data were transformed to conform, when possible, to the data standards of the National Wildfire Coordinating Group (NWCG), including an updated wildfire-cause standard (approved August 2020). Basic error-checking was performed and redundant records were identified and removed, to the degree possible. The resulting product, referred to as the Fire Program Analysis fire-occurrence database (FPA FOD), includes 2.3 million geo-referenced wildfire records, representing a total of 180 million acres burned during the 29-year period. Identifiers necessary to link the point-based, final-fire-reporting information to published large-fire-perimeter and operational-situation-reporting datasets are included.  Short, Karen C. 2022. Spatial wildfire occurrence data for the United States, 1992-2020 [FPA_FOD_20221014]. 6th Edition. Fort Collins, CO: Forest Service Research Data Archive. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2737/RDS-2013-0009.6">https://doi.org/10.2737/RDS-2013-0009.6</a>

- Creation Method:  Rocky Mountain Research Station (U.S. Forest Service) scientist, Karen Short, is the principal creator of this data set. Points were converted to 30m raster cells using the “most frequent” function on the NWCG_CAUSE_CLASSIFICATION attribute (Broad classification of the reason the fire occurred) creating three rasters:<p>- Human caused ignition</p><p>- Lightning (natural) caused ignition</p><p>- All causes of ignition - Human or Natural and Missing data/not specified/undetermined</p><p>“MostFrqCau” indicates the most frequent cause of the fire in that location.. “FireCount” indicates the number of fires that occurred between 1992 and 2020, regardless of cause. It is noted that locations with hundreds of counts may be a result of the method of how ignitions are reported/recorded. Both the accuracy and precision of the location estimates are generally much lower than that implied by the stored coordinate information – which, for example, may have been calculated from a PLSS section centroid. Efforts were made to purge redundant records to the best of the authors’ ability. Despite this, some locations may have multiple records that may reflect redundant records or multiple reports of fires due to the imprecision of the location record, the reporting process of an individual authority, or the possible reality of multiple initiations at a given location.   </p>


</idAbs><resConst /><resConst /><idCitation><resTitle>WldfireIgnCauseHuman_19922020_202312_T1_v5.tif</resTitle><date><pubDate>2022-09-30</pubDate></date><presForm><PresFormCd value="005" /></presForm><presForm><fgdcGeoform>raster digital data</fgdcGeoform></presForm><citRespParty><rpOrgName>USDA California Climate Hub</rpOrgName><rpOrgName>USDA California Climate Hub</rpOrgName><rpIndName>Peter A. Stine</rpIndName><rpPosName>Project Policy Analyst 5</rpPosName><role><RoleCd value="007" /></role><displayName>Peter A. Stine</displayName><displayName>Peter A. Stine</displayName></citRespParty><citRespParty><rpIndName>Carol Clark</rpIndName><rpPosName>Project Policy Analyst 4</rpPosName><role><RoleCd value="007" /></role><displayName>Carol Clark</displayName></citRespParty></idCitation><idStatus><ProgCd value="001" /></idStatus><resMaint><maintFreq><MaintFreqCd value="012" /></maintFreq></resMaint><themeKeys><keyword>environment, geoscientific Information, planning Cadastre, land management, landscape restoration</keyword><thesaName><resTitle>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</resTitle></thesaName></themeKeys><searchKeys><keyword>environment</keyword><keyword>geoscientific Information</keyword><keyword>planning Cadastre</keyword><keyword>land management</keyword><keyword>landscape restoration</keyword></searchKeys><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd value="002" /></spatRpType><dataChar><CharSetCd value="004" /></dataChar><tpCat><TopicCatCd value="007" /></tpCat><tpCat><TopicCatCd value="008" /></tpCat><tpCat><TopicCatCd value="015" /></tpCat><tpCat><TopicCatCd value="002" /></tpCat></dataIdInfo><spatRepInfo><Georect><numDims>2</numDims><axisDimension type="001"><dimSize>3300</dimSize></axisDimension><axisDimension type="002"><dimSize>2550</dimSize></axisDimension><cellGeo><CellGeoCd value="002" /></cellGeo></Georect></spatRepInfo><Esri><ArcGISFormat>1.0</ArcGISFormat><scaleRange><minScale>150000000</minScale><maxScale>5000</maxScale></scaleRange><DataProperties><itemProps><imsContentType export="False" /></itemProps></DataProperties><ArcGISProfile>FGDC</ArcGISProfile></Esri><mdContact><rpIndName>Peter A. Stine</rpIndName><rpOrgName>USDA California Climate Hub</rpOrgName><rpPosName>Project Policy Analyst 5</rpPosName><role><RoleCd value="007" /></role><displayName>Peter A. Stine</displayName></mdContact><mdContact><rpIndName>Carol Clark</rpIndName><rpOrgName>USDA California Climate Hub</rpOrgName><rpPosName>Project Policy Analyst 4</rpPosName><role><RoleCd value="007" /></role></mdContact></metadata>